A Guide to the Stokesville and North River Gap Oral Histories, 1996-1997: SdArch 35
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Stokesville and North River Gap Oral Histories
1996-1997
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Geier, Clarence R.
Veith, Kay
Chapman, C. Thomas
Monger, Kathryn
SdArch 35
.42 cubic feet; 1 box, 14 audiocassettes
The Stokesville and North River Gap Oral Histories, 1996-1997, are comprised of audio interviews, census data, genealogy research and scans of photographs related to prominent families of the North River Gap area and town of Stokesville, in Augusta County, Virginia.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access to oral histories is governed by agreements with the narrators. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Materials were transferred by Dr. Clarence Geier on September 11, 2017.
Biographical / Historical
The collection is comprised of research materials created by Kay Veith, Kathryn Monger and C. Thomas Chapman, James Madison University students who took courses taught by Dr. Clarence Geier, professor of Anthropology. Their research contributed to the book, "North River Gap – Stokesville, Augusta County, Virginia: A Selected Genealogy and Oral History of Residents," authored by Kay Veith, with contributions by Carole Nation and Clarence Geier, published in 1996. The project was a joint venture between members of the JMU history and anthropology departments, and the George Washington and Jefferson National Forests of Roanoke. Photograph scans were made from photographs belonging to individuals that participated in field survey.
Dr. Clarence Geier is a professor emeritus of Anthropology at James Madison University, where one of his primary research areas was the archeology of the American Civil War, specifically in the Shenandoah Valley. Kay Veith, who conducted many of the oral histories in this collection, was a student at JMU in the mid-1990s. Veith was a member of the Massanutten Chapter of the Archeological Society of Virginia, where she served as Secretary and chief organizer. Veith conducted fieldwork on many projects, including the Shenandoah National Park Archaeological Survey Program in the early 2000s. James Madison University established the Kay Veith Field Archeology Award to support young archeologists. Kathryn Monger undertook the geneology project on Reba Sirk Floyd.
Scope and Content
The Stokesville and North River Gap Oral Histories, 1996-1997, is comprised of audiorecordings and research files from the professional papers of Dr. Clarence Geier, a professor emeritus of Sociology and Anthropology at James Madison University. Materials include recordings, scanned photographs and other documents gathered from oral histories conducted with people in the Stokesville, and North River Gap area in August County. Narrators in the recordings discuss various topics, including the practice of tanbarking, the flood of 1949 in Stokesville, buildings in Stokesville, the Mt. Solon CCC camp, and personal family histories. The collection also contains genealogical studies of the North River Gap area.
Family names represented in the collection include Maichel, Sheffer (Scheffer, Shaver), Hise, Cramer, Loyd, Floyd, Todd, Daggy, Wilfong, Sirk, Karicofe, among others.
Related Resources
"North River Gap – Stokesville, Augusta County, Virginia: a selected geneology and oral history of residents" Kay Veith; with contributions by Carole Nash and Clarence R. Geier. James Madison University, Dept. of Sociology and Anthropology, 1999.
Arrangement
The interviews are arranged alphabetically by last name, and further arranged chronologically.
Bibliography
Nash, Carole. "Kay Veith Named ASV Avocational Archaeologist of the Year," Archeological Society of Virginia Massanutten Chapter. Volume 35, Issue 11, November 2014. http://www.mcasv.org/Points/NOV_2014.pdf (accessed on July 23, 2018).
Index Terms
Subjects:
Civilian Conservation Corps (U.S.). Camp Mt. Solon -- History; Mountain people -- Virginia -- Augusta County -- Social life and customs; Mountain life -- Virginia -- Augusta County -- History; Tanneries -- Virginia -- Augusta County -- History; Lumber trade -- Virginia -- Augusta County -- History; Buildings -- Virginia -- Augusta County; Augusta County (Va.) -- History; Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- History; Todd family; Lloyd family; Michael family; Shaffer family; Floyd family; Heiss family; Wilfong family
Genre and Form Terms:
oral histories (literary works); Cramer family
- Augusta County Census Data from 1840, 1850, 1860 from the North River Gap, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- List of Family Names from the North River Gap Area, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Kiracofe Family Biographies and Stokesville histories, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Reba Sirk Floyd Genealogy Project, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Floyd Family Photograph Scans, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Huffer Family Photograph Scans, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Sirk Family Photograph Scanst, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Stokesville, VA and Cass, WV Photograph Scans, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Unidentified Scans, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- SdArch 35-1: Alan Cramer, interviewed by Kay Veith, October 28, 1996
  - Supporting documentation (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Original audiocassette #1 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA035-CS-001)
  - Original audiocassette #2 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA035-CS-002)
- SdArch 35-2: Alan Cramer, interviewed by Kay Veith, November 12, 1996
  - Supporting documentation (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Original audiocassette #1 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA035-CS-003)
  - Original audiocassette #2 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA035-CS-004)
- SdArch 35-3: H. Russell Daggy Sr., interviewed by Kay Veith, March 7, 1997
  - Supporting documentation (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audiocassette SA035-CS-005)
- SdArch 35-4: Leon S. Kiracofe, interviewed by Kay Veith, February 19, 1997
  - Supporting documentation (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Original audiocassette #1 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA035-CS-006)
  - Original audiocassette #2 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA035-CS-014)
- SdArch 35-5: Clarence "Boxie" Loyd, interviewed by Kay Veith, November 27, 1996
  - Supporting documentation (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Original audiocassette #1 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA035-CS-007)
  - Original audiocassette #2 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA035-CS-008)
- SdArch 35-6: Clarence "Boxie" and Sophia Loyd, interviewed by Kay Veith, December 11, 1996
  - Supporting documentation (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Original audiocassette #1 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA035-CS-009)
  - Original audiocassette #2 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA035-CS-010)
- SdArch 35-7: Clarence "Boxie" Loyd and Martha Knott (Huffer family), interviewed by (Kay Veith?), December 27, 1996
  - Supporting documentation (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audiocassette SA035-CS-011)
- SdArch 35-8: Clarence "Boxie" Loyd, interviewed by Kay Veith, February 11, 1997
  - Supporting documentation (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audiocassette SA035-CS-012)
- SdArch 35-9: Sophia Loyd, interviewed by Kay Veith and Amy Carmichael, February 11, 1997
  - Supporting documentation (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audiocassette SA035-CS-013)